Hello and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan and today we're going to
be learning about acid base titrations
and specifically we're going to learn
all about how to find the concentration
of a, of these different solutions when
you are trying to mix them together.
Now with these, the whole idea here,
what we're trying to figure out with
concentration is we are doing molarity.
So what exactly is a titration?
Let's start with the basics.
So generally what it is, is whenever
you have, let's say a burette, which is
this long piece of glassware over here,
that's a very accurate piece of glassware.
And you're trying to control how
much solution you are reacting,
let's say with another vessel.
So in this case, I have an acid with an
indicator in this Erlenmeyer flask and
a base up in this, uh, burette up here.
Now, one thing that what, what
exactly are we using this for?
Well, it's generally used to
determine the unknown concentration
by reacting a precise volume of
solution, such as an acid in this
situation, with a precise volume of
another solution, such as a base.
Now the thing that's different
is the other solution, you
know the concentration.
So one of them is unknown
and the other is known.
And the whole idea here is you're
trying to figure out the exact point.
where they neutralize each other.
So that way you can get ideas of maybe
what the equivalence point is, when the
concentrations are equal to each other,
how exactly the acid and base behaves.
It gives you ideas about concepts
known as equilibrium, about pH,
how exactly a buffer could work,
which is another acid base concept.
is a very widely used concept that
is used very regularly in chemistry,
in the health sciences, and biology,
um, where we're really trying to
focus on acid base neutralization.
Now, what exactly does this refer to,
just to kind of as a little reminder,
is acid base neutralization is a double
replacement reaction, so it's a subtype.
Now, specifically neutralize
means that we're taking out the
acid in the base characteristics,
which are extremely dangerous.
Now how do we take them out is
we can make salt and water as a
product to help take those out.
Okay, so we're measuring essentially
the loss of acid, the loss of base.
So, whenever we're looking at these,
acids always have H as its main
characteristic, and bases always have
OH so when we add these two together,
we're always going to be making a
happy water molecule as a result.
So, let's take a look at a little bit
more about the vocabulary behind this
before we solve a couple problems.
The biggest component here is
that we are going to be doing
something like this in the lab.
Meaning that we'll need a couple
important piece of a piece
of glassware available to us.
So typically we're always using
a burette and a flask together.
Now the reason we use a burette is
that we can actually very accurately
control this flow knob here to
be able to flow out liquid at a
very, at any rate that you choose.
Whether it's really slow, very
fast, but it's very precise.
It goes to a very high
number of decimal places.
It's one of the more accurate and
precise piece of glassware that
you, that we have at our disposal.
Uh, the other thing that we'll use is
an indicator, which is commonly used
in biology and chemistry to denote
when a chemical reaction occurs.
So what an indicator does is
that, well, it indicates when
this happens via a color change.
So it's something that you can
perceive easily in the lab without
needing any fancy equipment.
Typically, it takes advantage
of pH changes or maybe if a
particular product is formed.
So that way you can actually
tell like, Oh, this happened.
It's very readily used in microbiology
as well as in chemistry and even
sometimes in physiology to determine
different macro molecules as well.
So when we are using these, the whole
idea here is being that we have, let's say
HCL, which is on the left hand side, and
we don't know what its concentration is.
Well, we can essentially figure
that out with a very specific, uh,
concentration of base, which we have 0.
100 molar base on the right of that.
So when we're using those, we
will add those two together.
And the whole idea is we are going
to be adding base very, very slowly.
Now as the pH changes, which we'll
talk about in future videos, eventually
this indicator is going to change
colors when the pH reaches zero.
that neutralization.
Now when we add bass very slowly what's
happening is remember H plus and OH
minus are combining to make water.
And the H plus is going to
keep decreasing, decreasing,
decreasing as we're going.
So it's going to keep progressing forward.
Now at some point, when will all
of a sudden it flip like a switch
and go from one to the other?
This is where the equivalence
point is, meaning where the
concentrations are equal to each other.
When can it go no farther and it's
going to turn pink in an instant.
So this is when it goes from acidic to
basic, and this is known as the end point.
So where do you stop the reaction, right?
So generally it's right, right
after that equivalence point
was reached is when you stop.
Whereas all of a sudden you have a
little bit more OH minus than H plus,
and this is something that we're going
to be doing in the lab in the future.
This is a whole idea of what these
types of reactions are and how
to calculate them is exactly what
volume or molarity is required to
neutralize these different solutions.
Let's go back to our practice problems.
You know, when you're in lab, sometimes
you, you write really quickly and
you can't read the notes later and
you don't know exactly what it is.
Well, this could be something
that's very dangerous, especially
when it comes to acids and bases.
So, we want to know what the concentration
is so we know exactly how to handle it.
So, what could we do to do that?
Well, this is when you can perform an
acid base titration, and what you will
do is we're going to place 20 milliliters
of the HCL in a flask with an indicator.
And what we have on hand, so we have 0.
1524 molar NaOH, and we're going
to place that in a burette.
And when we place it in the
burette, we have an initial
reading of 55 milliliters of base.
So this is exactly where it's
starting on the top of the burette.
Now keep in mind, burettes are all
about how much are you dispensing.
So if the volume starts at 55 milliliters,
that doesn't mean you only have 55.
It's where the label starts.
So when you perform the
experiment, the end point reach,
now what the volume says is 33.
87 milliliters.
So we dispense from 0.
55 to 33.
87.
So what is the concentration of HCl?
How do we go through a problem like that?
That seemed a little confusing.
What should we do?
So let's go through the steps,
exactly what we need to do here.
So the first part of this is that we
need to predict and balance the problem.
Okay, so that's always the first thing.
Right, so being that we have HCl plus
NaOH, well, we're going to do inside
outside, and I showed this one before.
Is that na is gonna bond with cl.
So cation always first and
then H with OH to make water.
And it's already balanced
with a one-to-one ratio.
So it's double replacement
with the following products.
Now, the main reason we're write
that writing this, uh, balance
equation is because we need to know
the mole ratios for these problems.
This one up here is a one-to-One reaction,
meaning all the coefficients are one,
but sometimes it's not the case, right?
You might have twos and threes or fours.
And that's going to affect your math.
The next thing is we need
to stay organized and write
down all the key terms.
So with this, right, we were
given the following problem, which
had a lot of information in it,
which was a little overwhelming.
So what we want to kind of do
is go through this and kind of
highlight what is important.
What do we know?
So the first thing is, is that we
had about 20 milliliters of HCl.
So let's write that down for ourselves.
off to the side.
So we have 20 mls of HCl.
Now what else do we have?
Well, we also were given the concentration
and the starting point and the end point
of our, of our, uh, sodium hydroxide
in this, in this reaction, right?
So we had the concentration
here, which was 0.
1524 molar.
And we also have the initial and
the end point of volumes as well.
So let's write all these
little values down.
So with that, right, with our
base concentration, we had for
sodium hydroxide, so we had 0.
1524 molar.
Then we had a final volume of 33.
0.
87 and a initial volume of 0.
55 milliliters for both
of these two values.
So what we are going to do is, uh,
the first thing is we are going to
follow our stoichiometry process
when we're going to look at these.
So we want to stay organized
and follow our mole map.
So let's do that for ourselves.
The first thing we're going to do is
we're going to follow our mole map.
So meaning that we need to kind of
map out the pieces that we have.
So when we do solution
stoichiometry, we want to go from
the volume of the base to moles.
Now, the reason we're going to start
with our base is because we know
the concentration and the volume.
You always start when you know
both those pieces of information.
Now, with titration, we need to calculate
what the volume is, though, in this
case, because if you notice, we were
given two different volumes, which is
where we started and where we ended.
So what we will do is we're going to
calculate the change in volume, which
is always known as the volume dispensed.
So how much is used in this reaction?
So we will just do final
minus initial, so 33.
87.
Minus 0.
55 milliliters, and this is going
to be how much volume we are
going to have in this problem.
So when we do the math, we
are going to have about 33.
32 milliliters at our disposal,
so that's how much we used.
Now what we are going to do is
we are going to start with the
given term that's by itself.
As you can see with this milliliter
value, it's a term that you can't
flip, it doesn't have a denominator.
So we are going to start
with that value and then use
molarity to convert it to moles.
So when we have 3 33 0.32 milliliters,
we're gonna convert this to liters first.
So we have a thousand MLS is one liter.
Now we'll use our molarity,
which was 0.1524 moles per liter.
Okay?
And that's of sodium hydroxide.
Now what we are going to do here
is we need to go to moles of acid.
So this is where the chemical
equation is useful, right?
It's a one to one ratio, meaning that we
have one mole of NaOH is equivalent to
every one mole of HCl in this problem.
You need to write that step down
because your units need to cancel.
All right, so we have one
mole NaOH, one mole HCl.
So now when we convert this,
what we are going to end up
getting is approximately 0.
005077968 moles of HCl.
But the thing is we want
to know the concentration.
So what do we need to figure
out concentration is, well,
you got to remember it's m is
equal to moles over liters.
And we were given the volume of
HCl that was used, which was 20
milliliters, which is approximately 0.
020 liters, right?
So when we divide those two
numbers, what we're going to end
up getting is a concentration of 0.
254 moles.
molarity as our answer.
So that's what the, the
unknown concentration was of
our chemical in this case.
So we do moles over liters is equal
to our concentration, which is
how we solve a titration problem.
Let's go on to one more example.
In a titration, if sulfuric
acid is neutralized by 0.
200 molar sodium hydroxide, With
an initial burette reading of 5 mL
and a final reading of 65 mL, what
is the concentration of the acid?
Okay, so the first thing we need
to do is we're going to predict
and balance our chemical equation.
So, being it's inside out, we'll take
sodium and combine it with sulfate.
So we'll have NA, and then we wanna
write the plus here, and then we'll
have sulfate, which is SO 42 minus.
We're gonna swap, drop their charges.
So the two of the sulfate is going
to come down next to sodium to
balance out the pluses and minuses.
And then we're going to be balanced.
Then we're gonna have h plus
and oh minus coming together.
So we have H plus oh minus.
Now these are technically just water,
so we're gonna, but we're gonna keep
it as HOH to help make balancing a
little bit easier in this problem.
So the first thing is, is that when
we are looking at this, is we want to
start with usually the polyatomics,
but right now your polyatomics are
balanced, so we have one sulfate on the
left and the right, and then we also
have one OH on the left and the right.
So, what we are going to do is
let's start with sodium, being that
there's two on the right, so we need
two on the left hand side as well.
So, now that we have that, we are
going to look at the hydroxides.
So there's one, there's two on
the left, and only one on the
right hand side right here.
So, what we will do is we're going
to put a two next to HOH, and as a
result, we look now at the hydrogens,
we see that we have two on the right,
and we also have two on the left.
Everything is now.
Nice and balanced so we can
kind of clean up our problem.
We can rewrite H2O And now we have a
completely balanced chemical reaction.
All right So now the first thing is
we need to stay organized when we are
writing out this problem So when we
are looking at this Generally, we want
to write down all the little piece of
information that we have when we are
seeing this So the first thing is is
that we have H2O 20 milliliters of H2SO4
and we also have a concentration of 0.
200 milliliters of
H2SO4 and we molar NaOH.
So, and there's also initial
and final volume reading.
So we need to figure out how
much a sodium hydroxide was used.
So when we're doing this, we, we ended
with 65 milliliters was our final reading
and we started with five milliliters.
So we're going to subtract those
two numbers and we're going to
see that we had 60 milliliters.
of, of, uh, sodium hydroxide that
was used in this problem, so that's
going to go with sodium hydroxide.
So when we're staying organized, this
is always the crucial detail that we
want to do, uh, when we are doing this
because it's going to make our problem
easier when we are doing our molar map.
Now let's go to that.
So the first thing is we want to map out
the problem, so we've got to start with
our volume because it's a term by itself.
So 60 milliliters, we need to convert this
to liters in order to use our molarity.
So being that our goal is always the
mole, so being that we have 1000 mLs
to 1 liter, this now puts our units
prime to be able to use our molarity.
molarity for our conversions.
So we have our molarity, which is 0.
200 molar NaOH.
So what we'll do is we'll put moles
of sodium hydroxide, and that's
equivalent to every one liter.
We want to now use our mole to
mole ratio, which as we see, this
is when balancing does matter.
We have two moles of sodium hydroxide.
is equivalent to every
one mole of sulfuric acid.
So this is where it does play
an impact in our calculations.
Now what we're going to do
with that is we're going to
figure out the number of moles.
So what we will see is we'll get 0.00006
moles of H two SO four, and what we
now need to do is divide this by the
volume, which was 20 milliliters,
so converted that, convert that to
liters, so 0.0 2, 0 0 liters, and we
will get a molarity of 0.3 hundred.
Molar, H2SO4, that's our answer.
So it's a little involved, but the
hardest part is kind of the end part.
You stop at moles and
then divide it by liters.
But I have a follow up question to this.
So what is the H plus concentration
in this sulfuric acid acid solution?
The one thing to keep in mind is
for a lot of you is that you'll
have new notation thrown at you all
the time in Chem 3A and one of the
biggest things is square brackets.
So if you ever see square brackets
around a number, so just like this H
plus here where you see the the orange
brackets, Well, this is referring
to concentration, meaning molarity.
So what is the H plus concentration here?
So being that we have 0.
300 Moles over every of H two SF four
over every liter, we can do a quick little
easy calculation based on dissociation.
So being that H two, SF four is
a strong acid, it's very soluble.
So that means that we have two
hydrogens that dissociate for
every sulfate ion in solution.
So we can label them as aqueous.
So that means that we have for
every one mole of H two, so four.
We have two moles of H
plus ion that are created.
So what is our concentration here?
Well, it's going to be 0.
3 times two.
So you're going to get
a concentration of 0.
600.
Molar for your H plus ion,
so that is your answer here.
So you can convert it for individual
ions too, which is a very valuable
skill to know, especially as we
start to get closer and closer to
understanding acid base reactions and
solving for pH, which is all about how
much hydrogen ion there is in solution.
Alright, so this is the end
of titrations and molarity.
Thank you so much for listening.
If this video helped
you, please let me know.
If it was a little confusing, reach
out and please message me, comment
below and tell me all about it.
Uh, if this is your first time here,
please hit that like button, subscribe
button, or refer to any of my other
videos to help you try to pass chemistry
and thank you so much for listening.
I'll see you all later.
Bye now.